## Alexander Pöppl, M.Sc.

https://apoeppl.github.io

#### **SUMMARY**

Researcher with 6 years of experience and 8 peer-reviewed publications in the field of HPC in both research and teaching. Made the case for the actor model as a parallelization technique for distributed HPC applications, and created libraries for it in X10 and modern C++. Enthusiastic about novel hard- and software techniques for exascale HPC applications.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Dr. rer. nat., Informatics

(Thesis Submitted)

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany,  $\sim 2021$ 

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Michael Bader

Title: Evaluation of the Actor Model for the Parallelization of Block-Structured Adaptive HPC Applications

#### M.Sc., Informatics

Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany, 2014

Focus: Compiler Construction, Mobile Application Development (iOS)

Thesis: Evaluation and Prediction of Execution Times for OpenCL-based Computations on GPGPU Systems

#### **B.Sc.**, Informatics

Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany, 2011

Minor: Business Studies

Thesis: Code Generation for Data Parallel Programs Using Restricted Polyhedron Array

Domains

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### **Research Associate**

12.2014 - 11.2019

- Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany
  Researched, implemented and successfully use
  - Researched, implemented and successfully used the actor model for blockstructured HPC applications. Implemented actor libraries for UPC++ and X10 and integrated them with a shallow water application. Evaluated the resulting performance benefits on a cluster of Many-Core CPUs.
  - Collaborated in an interdisciplinary team comprising researchers from the field of integrated circuit design, operating systems, compiler construction, embedded software and HPC to demonstrate the benefits of hardware-software co-design proposed by the Invasive Computing transregional research project.
  - Organized and planned the chair's yearly retreat.

## Affiliate (Research Stay)

08.2018 - 10.2018

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL), Berkeley, California, USA

• Implemented an actor library for large-scale HPC applications using the UPC++ communication library developed at LBNL.

## System Analyst, System Developer

04.2013 - 09.2014

Rivent GmbH, Munich, Germany

#### **Student Tutor** 10.2010 - 03.2013

Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany

#### **SKILLS**

- HPC: X10, UPC++, MPI, OpenMP, CUDA, Charm++, HPX
- *iOS*: Objective-C, UIKit, Swift
- Misc: Java, C++, Standard ML (programming language), UML, Python
- Languages: English, German

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] M. Bogusz, P. Samfass, A. Pöppl, J. Klinkenberg, and M. Bader, "Evaluation of Multiple HPC Parallelization Frameworks in a Shallow Water Proxy Application with Multi-Rate Local Time Stepping", in *PAW-ATM: Parallel Applications Workshop, Alternatives To MPI+X*, To Appear, IEEE, Nov. 2020.
- [2] A. Pöppl, M. Bader, and S. Baden, "A UPC++ Actor Library and Its Evaluation on a Shallow Water Proxy Application", en, in 2019 IEEE/ACM Parallel Applications Workshop, Alternatives To MPI (PAW-ATM), IEEE, Denver, Colorado, United States of America: IEEE/ACM/SigArch, Nov. 2019, pp. 11–24. DOI: 10.1109/PAW-ATM49560.2019.00007.
- [3] A. Pöppl, M. Damschen, F. Schmaus, A. Fried, M. Mohr, M. Blankertz, L. Bauer, J. Henkel, W. Schröder-Preikschat, and M. Bader, "Shallow Water Waves on a Deep Technology Stack: Accelerating a Finite Volume Tsunami Model Using Reconfigurable Hardware in Invasive Computing", in *Euro-Par 2017: Parallel Processing Workshops*, D. B. Heras, L. Bougé, G. Mencagli, E. Jeannot, R. Sakellariou, R. M. Badia, J. G. Barbosa, L. Ricci, S. L. Scott, S. Lankes, and J. Weidendorfer, Eds., Cham: Springer International Publishing, Feb. 2018, pp. 676–687, ISBN: 978-3-319-75178-8. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-75178-8\_54.
- [4] A. Pöppl and M. Bader, "SWE-X10: An Actor-based and Locally Coordinated Solver for the Shallow Water Equations", in *Proceedings of the Sixth ACM SIG-PLAN X10 Workshop (X10)*, Extended Abstract, Santa Barbara, CA, USA: ACM, Jun. 2016. DOI: 10.1145/2931028.2931034.
- [5] A. Pöppl, M. Bader, T. Schwarzer, and M. Glaß, "SWE-X10: Simulating Shallow Water Waves with Lazy Activation of Patches Using Actorx10", in 2016 Second International Workshop on Extreme Scale Programming Models and Middleware (ESPM2), Nov. 2016, pp. 32–39. DOI: 10.1109/ESPM2.2016.010.
- [6] S. Roloff, A. Pöppl, T. Schwarzer, S. Wildermann, M. Bader, M. Glaß, F. Hannig, and J. Teich, "ActorX10: An Actor Library for X10", in *Proceedings of the Sixth ACM SIGPLAN X10 Workshop (X10)*, Santa Barbara, CA, USA: ACM, Jun. 2016. DOI: 10.1145/2931028.2931033.
- [7] S. Wildermann, M. Bader, L. Bauer, M. Damschen, D. Gabriel, M. Gerndt, M. Glaß, J. Henkel, J. Paul, A. Pöppl, S. Roloff, T. Schwarzer, G. Snelting, W. Stechele, J. Teich, A. Weichslgartner, and A. Zwinkau, "Invasive computing for timing-predictable stream processing on MPSoCs", it Information Technology, vol. 58, no. 6, pp. 267–280, Jun. 2016. DOI: 10.1515/itit-2016-0021.
- [8] A. Pöppl and A. Herz, "A Cache-Aware Performance Prediction Framework for GPGPU Computations", in Euro-Par 2015: Parallel Processing Workshops, S. Hunold, A. Costan, D. Giménez, A. Iosup, L. Ricci, M. E. Gómez Requena, V. Scarano, A. L. Varbanescu, S. L. Scott, S. Lankes, J. Weidendorfer, and M. Alexander, Eds., Cham: Springer International Publishing, Dec. 2015, pp. 749–760, ISBN: 978-3-319-27308-2. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-27308-2\_60.

#### **REFERENCES**

References provided upon request.